A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Washington, DC, Series O FA350
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Special Committee on Government Organization (SCOGO), Reorganization Advisory Committee (RAC), President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization (PACGO), November 1952-December 1958; 5; 14.8 Cubic Feet; 12 document boxes 67 bound volumes
  - President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization (PACGO), November 1952-December 1958; O_5C
    - President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization (PACGO) Bound Volumes, 1949-1958
      - Department of the Interior, 1953-1954 (Volume 43)
        A. Background to 1953 Study of Interior Department; B. Temple University Report - Comments by Budget and other persons; C. Draft proposal (1953) and related memoranda; D. Final Recommendation to President, March 14, 1953; E. Bureau of Land Management; F. Corps of Engineers (See Vol. 39 for Transportation aspects of Corps of Engineers); G. 1954 Study by Interior on reorganization of that Department.
      - Water Resources Policy, 1954-1955 (Volume 44)
        A. Cabinet Committee -- Background papers (See Vol. 43 for Corps of Engineers papers); B. Cabinet Committee Establishment, May 1954; C. Inter-Agency Agreement on the Coordination of Water and Related Land Resources Activities - President's letter approving its establishment, May 26, 1954; D. Request for Progress Reports and date requested for Final Report (Cabinet Committee); E. Staff of Cabinet Committee; F. Minutes of Meetings and drafts of Interim Report (Cabinet Committee); G. Interim Report - Cabinet Committee, December 14, 1954; H. Proceedings of Cabinet Committee prior to Final Report; I. Cabinet Committee Report, December 22, 1955 (with press release); J. Implementation of Report on Water Resources Policy (General Bragdon).
      - Department of the Post Office; Deparment of the Treasury, 1952-1953 (Volume 45)
        Post Office: A. 1953 Study, Background and related correspondence; B. Temple University Survey, Dec. 30, 1952, with budget and other comments; C. Postmaster's Plan for the Post Office Department, April, 1953; D. Reorganization Plan No. 10 of 1953, Airline Subsidies (See Vol. 39 for background).Treasury: E. 1953 Study - Background and Related memoranda. Includeds Reconstruction Finance Corporation, Export-Import Bank (See also Vol. 47), U.S. Coast Guard; F. Temple University Survey with comments; G. Final Recommendation to President, March 14, 1953; H. Reorganization Plan No. 5 of 1953 (Export-Import Bank).
      - Veterans Administration, 1952-1956 (Volume 46)
        1953 Recommendations:A. Background with drafts and related memoranda; B. Temple University Survey reports, Jan. 12, 1953 and Feb. 17, 1953, with Budget and other comments; C. Organization Charts, Existing (1952), Recommended by Booz, Allen & Hamilton (June 1952), Recommended by Carl Gray, Adm. of V.A., Nov 1952; D. American Legion Correspondence and Meetings; E. Final Recommendation to President - April 1953; F. Budget letter to V.A. re implementation of recommendations of Organization Committee.
        Bradley Commission Study of V.A.:G. Bradley Report - April 1956 (with related correspondence); H. PACGO's recommendation to President, February 1957, on Cabinet Status of V.A.
      - Foreign Affairs Organization, 1952-1953 (Volume 47)
        A. Background papers prior to 1953 study; B. Drafts of recommendations to President, with Agency and other comments, Minutes of meetings concerning views and the various drafts, Dec. 1952 - March 1953; C. Temple University Survey of foreign affairs and mutual security organization; D. USIA, background & Psychological Strategy Board papers on establishment of a new agency; E. Commerce Secretary views on foreign capital investment.; F. Meeting with President, April 2, 1953, with draft report; G. Draft of Report, approved by President and agencies; H. Final Report to President - April 9, 1953; I. Export-Import Bank - correspondence re plan.; J. Reorganization Plan No. 5 of 1953 - Export-Import Bank; K. Reorganization Plan No. 7 of 1953 - Foreign Operations Adm.; L. Reorganization Plan No. 8 of 1953 - U.S. Information Agency; M. Plans Nos. 7 and 8 of 1953, with Associated Executive Orders; N. Dirksen Subcommittee investigation "Trading with the Enemy Act."
      - Foreign Affairs: Miscellaneous (Volume 48)
        A. OCB Organization (See files of Special Assistant to President for background and subsequent correspondence); B. Institute of Inter-American Affairs (See Volume covering FOA transfer to State Dept.); C. Attaches - Agricultural; D. Attaches - Commercial; E. Attaches - Social Welfare; F. Coordination Within U.S. Overseas Missions; G. Cultural and Exchange of Persons Programs; H. Relief and Refuge Programs.
      - Foreign Affairs: Council on Foreign Economic Policy (Volume 49)
        A. Background to Study on Foreign Economic Policy; B. Hoover Commission Activities in Area; C. Presidential Directive to PACGO and Budget Bureau, and Organization for Study; D. Appointment of Mr. Joseph Dodge to make study; E. Dodge Questions to Agencies; F. Interim Report, September 10, 1954; G. Dodge memorandum of September 14, 1954, on Considerations Relating to the Problem; H. Reports of Agencies (in response to questions, see E above); I. Dodge Interim Report to President, October 4, 1954; J. Draft report, October 21, 1954; K. Semi-final Report to President (Discussed with and approved by President, November 15, 1954); L. Dodge Appointment as Chairman of Council on Foreign Economic Policy.
      - Foreign Affairs: Mutual Security Programs Part 1, 1955 (Volume 50)
        A. Transfer of FOA to State, 1955 - Background papers and drafts; B. Jack Ohly's recommendations for conduct of Foreign Aid Programs, April 7, 1955, with particular reference to MDAP Program; C. President's announcement of transfer of FOA to State, April 15, 1955; D. Mutual Security Program - Drafts and correspondence re President's Message to Congress, for FY 1956; E. President's Message to Congress, FY 1956 Program for Mutual Security; F. Drafts of Executive Order transferring FOA to State; G. Executive Order #10610, May 9, 1955, transferring FOA to State.
      - Foreign Affairs: Mutual Security Programs Part 2, 1955-1957 (Volume 51)
        A. Procedures for Implementation of FOA transfer to State, Draft papers and recommendations; B. Hughes-Rockefeller memorandum to State, re administration of Mutual Security Program, June 13, 1955; C. Secy of State Order establishing International Cooperation Administration in State, June 30, 1955; D. President's Executive Order of August 2, 1955, re MDAP; E. ICA Organizational Developments, and PACGO's role in their implementation, 1955 and 1956; F. State-ICA Relationships - State paper of February 1956; G. Report of IDAB (Eric Johnston, Chairman), March 1957; H. Fairless Committee Report on the Mutual Security Program, March 1, 1957; I. Executive Order #10742, November 30, 1957, giving Secy of State greater flexibility and control in the organization of Mutual Security responsibilities and activities within the State Department.
      - Foreign Affairs Organization, 1957-1958 (Volume 52)
        A. Background to Proposal for a Department of Foreign Affairs and/or an appointed Vice President; B. Analyses of Various Issues (Burton, Pollack & Kimball (papers); C. Concept of a First Secretary of the Government and a Department of International Relations. Study by PACGO, January-April, 1957; D. Foreign Affairs Organization, Papers for May & June, 1957; E. Proposal Discussed with President, June 18, 1957; F. Organization for International Affairs, Nov. 1957, May 1958, as discussed with Secretary Dulles; G. Task Force Study to develop Recommendations, May-Dec. 1958 (meeting with President, December 6, 1958); H. Proposed Reorganization of State Department (discussed with Secretaries Herter & Dillon, December 21, 1958, with Charts prepared by State).
      - Department of Defense: Background for 1953 Study Part 1, 1945-1953 (Volume 53)
        I. National Security Act of 1947 A. Act, as amended: September 1, 1949; January 8, 1952 (with summary); June 28, 1952; April 4, 1953; August, 1953
        B. Legislative History of the National Security Act of 1947, and its Amendments 1. Background Summary of Organizational Concepts in the National Security Act - March 18, 1953
        2. Letter of Secretaries Patterson (War) and Forrestal (Navy) to the President - May 31, 1946.
        3. President's reply to above letter - June 15, 1946.
        4. The B-36 Investigation of 1949 - Historical paper.
        II. Key West and Newport Agreements (Agreement April 21, 1948, w/changes to March 16, 1954) A. Summaries of Decisions, and Functions of the Armed Forces B. Text of Agreements
        C. Summary of Newport Decisions.
        III. Hoover Commission Report, February 1949 A. Text of Report - The National Security Organization (See Tab G of Vol. 14 for Task Force Report)
        B. Current Status of Major Proposals (February 9, 1953)
        C. Excerpt from Task Report - Nov. 15, 1948.
        IV. Organization Charts Department of Defense; Department of the Army; Department of the Navy; Department of the Air Force
        V. Joint Chiefs of Staff A. Organization Chart (July 1952) and Roster (April 1953) B. Organization, authority and responsibilities (September 1952) C. Legislative Background of Statutory Provisions Dealing with the Chair JCS and the Joint Staff, June 15, 1953 D. Current Administrative Procedures of the JCS - June 16, 1953 E. Outline of Differences in Duties of the Military Chiefs F. Role, Relationships and Organization of the JCS, Dec. 15, 1952 G. Representative Shafer's Speeches March 11 and 23, 1953 (Prussian Staff) H. John J. McCloy - Excerpts from Godkin Lectures, Jan. 12-14, 1953. I. Lt. Gen. H. S. Aurand to Milton Eisenhower, March 7, 1953.
        VI. Role of Secretary of Defense vis-a-vis Military Chiefs and Departments A. Memoranda concerning the assignment of separate Statutory Authority to the MIlitary Departments, March 1953
        B. Memoranda on "Gray Areas"
        C. Secretary Army Gordon Gray and Mr. Stimpson correspondence, re role of Secretary of the Army with Army Chief of Staff
        D. Harold H. Martin article March 14, 1953, Saturday Evening Post, The Toughest Job Facing Ike.
        E. Lord Hankey, Government Control in War, 1945, Chapter I, "Principles."
      - Department of Defense: Background for 1953 Study Part 2, 1951-1953 (Volume 55)
        VII. Comments and Reports on Defense Organization A. Secretary Wilson (memoranda and letters to Nelson Rockefeller) 1. Letter of February 13, 1953 (with General Motors Chart)
        2. Memo of February 26, 1953, stating his basic concept for organization of Defense Department.
        B. Secretary Lovett 1. Mr. Coolidge's memo to Sec. Lovett, September 1952.
        2. Mr. Lovett's letter to President, Nov. 18, 1952 (with summary)
        3. JCS study, March 20, 1953, based on concepts stated in Mr. Lovett's letter (A Committee Study on the Organization of DOD)
        C. Dr. Vannevar Bush 1. Summary of following items: 2. Speech of September 26, 1952 3. Speech of October 11, 1952 4. Collier's article, December 27, 1952 5. National War College Speech, February 12, 1953
        D. General David Sarnoff 1. Sarnoff Commission Report, February 17, 1953 (Citizens Advisory Commission on Manpower Utilization in the Armed Services)
        2. General Sarnoff's analysis of report and annexes
        E. Thomas K. Finletter Speech (with summary) at National War College, January 18, 1953
        F. Stuart Symington 1. Report (as Chairman of NSRB), March 31, 1951 - re JCS & Munitions Board
        2. Speech at Philadelphia, March 11, 1953.
        VIII. Miscellaneous Reports and Suggestions A. Heller Report on Management - December 15, 1951
        B. Hebert Special Subcommittee on Procurement
        C. Bonner Committee Studies of Federal Supply Activities
        D. Lewis L. Strauss - Summary of report on Procurement of Material for the Armed Forces, March 9, 1951 and May 21, 1952.
        E. British Defense Organization - Article from London Times, February 17, 1953.
        F. Senator Flanders
        G. Congressman Ellsworth
        H. Henry N. Sachs
        I. Stephen J. Spingarn (re Counter Intelligence Corps)
        J. Reserve Officers Training Association of the U.S.
        IX. Miscellaneous papers re Defense Organization and Policies A. International Affairs
        B. Research and Development
        C. Munitions Board
        D. Secretary Wilson's directive re procurement
        E. Joint Organizations in the DOD
        F. Director of Installations.
      - Department of Defense: 1953 Study and Report (Volume 55)
        A. Appointment of Committee, Members and Staff; B. Meetings of March 2 and March 9, 1953 (see index with tab); C. Meetings of March 20-22, 1953 (see index with tab) Includes lists of questions for witnesses; D. Meetings of March 28-30, 1953 (see index with tab); E. Meetings of April 4-6, 1953 (see index with tab); F. Meetings of April 10-12, 1953 (see index with tab); G. Draft Report, with charts, and schedule for handling of report; H. Report of Rockefeller Committee, April 11, 1953 with letter from Secretary Wilson.
      - Department of Defense: 1953 Report Implementation (Volume 56)
        A. Reorganization Plan No. 6 of 1953; B. Congressional correspondence and testimony of Mr. Rockefeller; C. Hearings (House) on Reorganization Plan No. 6; D. Correspondence re Herbert Hoover approval of Plan; E. Navy Department Organization Report, April 1954; F. Army Department (Davies) Report - December 1953; G. Vannevar Bush correspondence re Rockefeller recommendation for Joint Strategic Survey Committee; with Defense Directive of July 26, 1954; H. Defense Legislation for additional Assistant Secretaries of the three Services, 1954; I. Quantico Defense Dept. Conference, June 1954, Sec. Army Stevens Organization Plan Organization charts and plans for Defense; J. Reorganization Plan No. 1 of 1956 for Assistant Secretaries of 3 services for R&D (defeated); K. Secretary of Defense conference May 1956 (Summary of actions taken on Rockefeller Report of 1953); L. Proposed Defense Advisory Committee - with Mr. Rockefeller's proposals for membership; M. Defense data on Hoover Commission recommendations (May 1956); N. Navy attack on Plan 6 of 1953 (Nov. 1956); O. Sec. Wilson's speech to National War College, June 11, 1957, re Defense Organization.
      - Department of Defense: Rockefeller Brothers Fund Study, 1957-1958 (Volume 57)
        A. Henry Kissinger article in Foreign Affairs, April 1957, "Strategy and Organization"
        B. Arnold Miles' study for RBF, April 1957, "Notes on Strengthening the Department of Defense."
        C. N. E. Halaby comments on Defense Organization, October 1957
        D. Soviet Sputnik -- Newspaper clippings, and memoranda by Anna Rosenberg and T. F. Walkowicz
        E. Henry Kissinger's draft "Notes on Reorganization of Department of Defense", October 12, 1957, with summary and charts.
        F. Henry Kissinger final paper on Defense Organization, Oct. 16, 1957 (Discussed with President and Secretary of Defense)
        G. Nelson Rockefeller Speech "The Challenge of the Budget in our Democracy", May 20, 1957
        H. RBF Report, January 1958 - International Security -- The Military Aspect
        I. Nelson Rockefeller statement, January 10, 1958 before Johnson Senate Preparedness Investigating Subcommittee on "Inquiry into Satellite and Missile Programs." (See Volumes 58 and 59 for Hearings)
        J. Nelson Rockefeller statement to House Appropriations Subcommittee (Hearings, January 1958. Cong. Mahon, Chairman)
        K. Joint Chiefs of Staff analysis of RBF Report.
        L. H. Struve Hensel analysis of RBF Report.
      - Department of Defense: Senator Johnson's Hearings on Satellite and Missile Programs Part 1, 1957-1958 (Volume 58)
      - Department of Defense: Senator Johnson's Hearings on Satellite and Missile Programs Part 2, 1958 (Volume 59)
      - Department of Defense Organization: House Hearings, 1958 April-May (Volume 60)
      - Department of Defense Organization: Senate Hearings, 1958 June-July (Volume 61)
      - Department of Defense Organization: Background and Laws, 1947-1958 (Volume 62)
        A. General Eisenhower's statements in 1945
        B. Statements of opinion by individuals knowledgeable re Defense Organization (1946-1957; Forestall, Lovett, etc.)
        C. Mr. Rockefeller's meeting with Secretary McElroy Oct. 17, 1957 (with Kissinger paper of Oct. 16 - see Vol. 57)
        D. Kimball memoranda re Defense situation and briefing by Col. Cook
        E. Mr. Rockefeller's meeting with President, Nov. 4, 1957, with background papers on Defense prepared by Budget Bureau
        F. PACGO memo to President Nov. 15, with draft proposal for reorganization of Defense Dept., dated Nov. 12, 1957
        G. Budget paper, listing statutory changes needed, in recommendations set forth in above Nov. 12 draft memo to President.
        H. Budget bill for establishment of Defense Institute for research
        I. Memoranda re progress on defense organization (See Vol. 63 for charts)
        J. Sec. McElroy's establishment of Defense Organization Committee, January 21, 1958
        K. Policy memoranda concerning progress and policy matters, February through May 1958
        L. Senator Bush's proposed legislation for reorganization of Defense, February 1958
        M. President's Message to Congress April 3, 1958, transmitting recommendations relative to Defense
        N. President's Bill of April 16, 1958, transmitting proposed legislation to amend the National Security Act of 1947, with H.R. 11958 introduced by Senator Martin.
        O. House Committee Hearing papers, with summary of reactions to President's bill (See Vol. 60 for Hearings)
        P. House bill, H.R. 12541, May 19, 1958 - Proposed by Mr. Vinson as result of House hearings, with House Report 1765 (accompany HR 12541)
        Q. President's Statements concerning House Bill, May 1958 (See Vol. 61 for Senate Hearings)
        R. Public Law 85-599, approved August 6, 1958.
      - Department of Defense Organization: Background for Study, 1951-1958 (Volume 63)
        1. National Security Act of 1947, as amended to August 1956; 2. Mr. Lovett letter to President Truman, November 18, 1952; 3. Rockefeller Report on Defense Organization, April 11, 1953; 4. Reorganization Plan No. 6 of 1953; 5. Key West Agreement, October 1, 1953 (as revised from April 21, 1948); 6. Roles and Missions of Defense, November 26, 1956; 7. Executive Agent Assignments for Unified and Specified Commands; 8. JCS, Method of Operation, July 26, 1954; 9. Joint Staff Organization (Chart); 10. OSD Organization Charts; 11. Miscellaneous documents; 12. Mr. Rockefeller's Organization Charts, January 1958: Material relating to Army, Navy and Air Force Organization; 13. JCS, Chart Briefing in January 1958; 14. Views of Witnesses and other principals; 15. William Foster's Scientific Presentation book; 16. Joint Action Armed Forces, September 1951 (with changes through January 3, 1958).
      - Department of Defense Organization: Committee Meeting Papers and Discussions, 1957-1958 (Volume 64)
        A. Agendas; B. Witnesses: Stanford Research Institute papers; C. Schedule of Meetings; D. Method of Procedure for Defense Organization group; E. Questions - Lists of, for witnesses; F. Summary of views of Witnesses and other principals; G. Minutes of Meetings; H. Major Statutory Changes needed (Budget paper, based on Tab J below); I. Budget Paper: Combatant Functions, Army, Navy, Marine Corps and Air Force; J. Rockefeller Proposal to President for Defense Organization, November 12, 1957; K. Kissinger Plan, October 16, 1957; L. Goodpaster (for President) directive to Budget & Defense, January 16, 1958; M. Power and Authority of the Secretary of Defense, 1953 Legal Opinion; N. Unified, Joint and Specified Commands; O. Rockefeller Brothers Fund Report, January 1958:With JCS Staff comments, February 3, 1958; P. JCS Planning Functions; Q. Navy Department Charts: World War II, October 1957; R. Weapons Systems; S. Mr. Rockefeller's Plan for February 20, 1958 for Organization, with Charts (Listing Present and Proposed Org.); T. Memorandum of quotations which support Mr. Rockefeller's position; U. Navy Plan for Organization for Defense, February 19, 1958; V. Mr. Coolidge's Suggestions for Organization of Defense; W. Drafts of Message to Congress (with analyses by Budget).
      - Department of Defense Organization: Views of Witnesses and Principals (Volume 65)
        A. Summary of Views for Mr. Rockefeller's Personal Use;B. Summary of Views, prepared by Defense Department;C. Full Text of Views (see index for persons giving views)
      - Department of Defense Organization: Newspaper Clippings (Volume 66)
      - Recommendations, 1953 April (Volume 67)
      - Index (Volume Index)
- Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW), June 1953-December 1954; 6; 16.8 Cubic Feet; 2 document boxes 116 bound volumes
  One of the recommendations of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization led to the creation of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. As Under Secretary, Rockefeller was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that greatly expanded the coverage of the Social Security program. Included in the bound volumes is Rockefeller's chronological out-going correspondence from his entire tenure in this position.
  - General, 1953-1955 (Box 57, Folder 481)
  - NAR as Under Secretary, 1953-1955 (Box 57, Folder 482)
  - Letters of Resignation, 1955 (Box 57, Folder 483)
  - Congratulatory Letters (A-I), 1953 (Box 57, Folder 483A)
  - Congratulatory Letters (J-Z), 1953 (Box 57, Folder 483B)
  - General Correspondence, 1953-1957 (Box 57, Folder 484)
  - Letters of Appreciation, 1955 (Box 57, Folder 485)
  - Daily Calendar, 1953 (Box 58, Folder 486)
  - Telephone Calls, 1953 (Box 58, Folder 487)
  - Clippings, 1953-1954 (Box 58, Folder 488)
  - Office Directories, 1953-1954 (Box 58, Folder 489)
  - Hobby, Secretary Oveta Culp, 1953-1956 (Box 58, Folder 490)
  - Personnel, 1953-1954 (Box 58, Folder 491)
  - Education, 1954-1955 (Box 58, Folder 492)
  - Health, 1954-1955 (Box 58, Folder 493)
  - Medical Research, 1952-1953 (Box 58, Folder 494)
  - Social Security, 1954-1955 (Box 58, Folder 495)
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW) Bound Volumes, 1953-1956
    - Secretary's Office/Departmental Council (Volume 1)
      A. Staff Organization, Secretary's Office
      B. Departmental Council - Creation and Functions
      C. Departmental Council - Agenda and Minutes
    - Under Secretary's Office (Volume 2)
      A. Pending and Action Items
      B. Under Secretaries Cabinet Meetings
      C. Speeches - Nelson A. Rockefeller
    - Status Reports, Part I, 1954 (Volume 3)
      A. Establishment of System
      B. Reports. Period: March 29, 1954 through September 2, 1954.
    - Status Reports, Part II, 1954 September 9-1955 January 20 (Volume 4)
      No Subnote Content
    - Presidential Policies (Volume 5)
    - Outside Agencies (Volume 6)
      A. Interdepartmental Committee on Migratory Labor
      B. Government Contracts Committee (Non-discrimination)
      C. Commission on Intergovernmental Relations
      D. Council of Economic Advisers
    - Organization and Management - Fry Report (Volume 7)
    - Organization and Management - Background Papers (Volume 8)
    - Organization and Management - Organizational Charts (Volume 9)
    - Organization and Management - General (Volume 10)
      A. Miscellaneous Reports and Correspondence
      B. International Affairs Activities
      C. Office of Inspection